all right welcome back call 5 we're in
our last
recorded meeting Andrew and all of us
will be talking about chapter 10 but
also kind of probably anything
goes
and yeah let's go there Andrew however
you want to proceed yep sure yeah I'll
just give
a quick kind of summary of this chap I
cannot give an entire holistic summary
of this chapter because as we know it
longest chapter in the textbook um and
one of its key themes is to describe
active inference is a basically a kind
of complete solution to sentient
organisms adaptive problems which
attempts to provide a unified
perspective on action selection
perception attention emotion regulation
of right of other cognitive
mechanisms um so it's it's it attempts
to give us I think a kind of like let's
round out the textbook here let's let's
let's go over in section
10.2 all of the previous chapters up to
this point give a quick summary like
kind of in a per paragraph approach for
each chapter reminding us of anything
from marov blankets to neurobiological
sub substats message
passing uh building models and so on um
section 10.3 quickly mentions this uh
the famous uh philosopher Daniel dennet
his suggestion to model the whole iguana
uh was the was the quote and that's more
or less what active inference attempts
to do by using free energy minimization
is a sort of first principle by which we
can derive implications for a variety of
cognitive
processes um it takes a kind of inactive
integrative approach to to behavior to
preference realization self- evidencing
self-preservation and autop
poesis um it does not separate entirely
action and perception as is done in uh
or has been done at least in different
um
neuropsychological uh
approaches and uh yeah it just attempts
to yeah just take a very integrated view
don't view action and perception as
totally separate don't view Memory and
attention is completely separate
planning prospection retrospection all
these things are are tied together by
way of a free energy minimization and
then from there for anyone who's you
know more more focused upon sort of the
the neural and neurobiological
substrates and
underpinnings neural signatures getting
into neuroimaging Data then it might
just be the case that we're looking at
different Pathways uh for each of these
things but nonetheless they're they're
sort of of a piece um and before I I
wrap up this this summary I mentioned I
I noticed at the end of section
10.3 they mentioned um uh reference this
this great
neuroscientist uh up at NYU Yori busak
who's kind of famous for um back around
2006 I believe 2004 2006 um talked to
began talking about this kind of inside
out approach to studying the the brain
and how the cognitive and psychological
Sciences have sort of inherited all of
these um Jamesy and William
jamesian uh categories in in how they
understand the the mind the the mind
brain connection and so on so these were
even these very words that we're using
uh memory and planning and
emotion uh you can just flip open like
one of James's like key books that's
been used as a foundation in many
Psychology and Neuroscience courses and
just yeah look at its t table of
contents and we have so many of these
these words that that are continuing to
be used in a very sometimes very free
floating kind of way uh in in current
research um what does memory mean uh
what what is attention exactly and uh
yeah so it's it's not to say that all
these jamesian categories should be you
know eliminated uh from from The
Sciences or you know reject did or even
uh supposed to have you know zero value
they have plenty of horis value but uh
it's just it's an interesting take to
try and use what we know now about
neurobiology about
computation
mathematics and yeah just maybe it's
time for the the cognitive sciences and
others to kind of update some of their
their taxonomies and
terminology uh that they use um for this
kind of work and and just consider like
more integrative perspectives and for
all these things that are treated
separately so anyway that's kind of my
two cents on that reference they make
and
um so from there we get um you know
these kind of mini
subsections uh that relate active
inference to just a broad variety of
other fields um its relationships its
different is um because they're able to
find kind of positive relationships
between active inference and these other
fields it kind of opens the door for
dialogue uh for control theory
predictive
processing um action control cybernetics
idiom motor theory it's it's I think
it's it's kind of it's it's doing
exactly what it purports to do which is
to find an integrated perspective um
then that said it distinguishes itself
um active inference is becoming its own
kind of approach framework uh body of
knowledge and so yeah it's uh it's just
kind of placing itself in the sort of
epistemic field that we we find
ourselves within and um relationships
with utility decision making
reinforcement learning so many people I
think come to active inference in part
because they want to study those things
whenever they're not coming from a more
neuroscientific background and it's like
well utility is kind of implicated in
active inference but but it's more than
that we have
epistemic value and we have balancing
between epistemic and pragmatic value
rather than treating them as their own
separate cost functions or ignoring one
of them or otherwise and finally the the
chapter points at sort of these other
fields in open directions um the idea of
modeling social and cultural Dynamics is
a kind of broader scale application of
active inference um you could even
presume that that goes down to the micro
level that is we have human beings
individuals with their own generative
models just interacting in a kind of
multi-agent environment and then from
there checking to see what are the
emergent behaviors whenever they
interact and so what kind of kind of
social dynamics happen what kind of
cultural creations and Productions they
they come up with um things like that so
um I think I'll leave it there for now
there's just too much to go over I won't
give like a point by Point like here's
the difference between active inference
and um you know reinforcement learning
right away or something but um that's
about
good stopping point I think so if anyone
has any you know points of interests
they want to talk about any kind of
questions something on their mind U
please feel free to go for it okay I
have a have a more of a it's yeah try to
explain it in simple words like I've you
seen this use of this word epistemic a
lot and it can make multiple things what
does the word epistemic mean in this in
the context of active
inference
yeah sure I'll I'll I'll give that a
shot um so previously in the textbook at
times we would see you know we've seen
different like kind of equations that
break down computation of variational
and expected free
energies and so we've seen how it can be
broken down into word like certain terms
that that have been given a nam so we
have like Risk ambiguity
um complexity accuracy so so two of
those terms that can be broken down into
are
pragmatic um value and epistemic value
and uh those are those are pretty
essential they relate to uh a classic
problem in the the social sciences
called the the explore exploit tradeoff
um but in simpler terms pragmatic value
as opposed to EP epistemic is something
like an agent just going for realizing
their goals directly like you're hungry
you want some food you go for the food
um you know realize that preference to
to you know diminish your hunger keep
your
homeostasis pretty aligned and balanced
um but epistemic value meanwhile would
be acting in order to get more
information
in order to realize your goal so again
you're hungry you want some food well
where can I get food like maybe it's
contextual where can I get food right
now um I you can use the internet search
up what places are open uh what what
places are delivering um how much money
do I have uh currently and what's my
budget so it would basically just be
kind of instrumentally you searching
seeking for information that can help
you to realize the goal so often times
Whenever there are like behavioral
experiments like a kind of two Arm
Bandit problem for example where an
agent can uh they can go
to uh they have multiple actions
available to them they can go uh
immediately to uh a reward like pulling
the slot machine at the the end of the
task or
prior to that they can go to a q
cuq that will inform them uh Which slot
machine to pull which one has the higher
probability of giving them a payoff and
so the agent um you know if the if the
agent doesn't care about the epistemic
value it could derive from the queue uh
giving it the information of how to
better realize its goal it'll just skip
the Quee go straight for for pragmatic
value pull the slot machine see if it
wins um so I I I hope that that was
helpful but I yeah I think that the
simplest terms are epistemic is
something like the knowing it's the it's
the information that'll help you get to
your goal pragmatic action and value are
derived from from actually going
directly at the goal so you collect
enough info you know what to do after
that you go for the pr Matic
value yeah a little bit of just other
broader pieces here
epistem in contrast with belief doca
like a
Creed also as distinguishing the the
knowledge from the Creed from the
technique which is the basis of
Technology um and then another helpful
piece like uh Andrew mentioned the
epistemic pragmatic value the epistemic
value is like known
unknowns in the prospective setting
because it's a value ascertainment about
a given policy how much I expect to
learn from that policy so of course if
something you didn't expect to learn
happened it couldn't have been
considered at the moment so that would
be an epistemic event like in the
broader sense of just epistemic meaning
learning or knowledge but when we're
talking about expect Ed free energy
equation
2.6 epistemic value is specifically
about expected Information Gain which
has to do with like how certain or
uncertain the agent is in the
moment and then the epistemic chaining
demo um which is just like one step it's
basically One Step more detail than in
the
textbook but um you see the mouse
navigate to The
Q but this just kind of begets other
questions like how does it come to
believe with with full Precision that
the Q is informative so this isn't the
whole iguana but this kind of isolates a
situation where either a risky pragmatic
decision can be approached immediately
or a little bit more of a cirous path
can be taken that results in Information
Gain results in observations that are
expected to reduce uncertainty about
where the preferred observations
are and then depending on how all the
parameters are set you could have an
agent that just still goes and risk it
risks it for the uncertain reward
sooner can we can we actually phrase it
like uh epistemic uh value and epistemic
capacity is like the potential of the
possible things which can be done and
the pragmatic things the actual thing
that we do so it's like EP epistemic
values are like uh as a ground on which
possible things can happen and pragmatic
thing is the actual thing that you
do like conversationally that might make
sense but when you're talking when you
say things that you could do that's
basically affordances
and affordances then can be evaluated in
terms of their epistemic and pragmatic
value but it isn't that something that
you can do is related to The Information
Gain of that
action but I mean conversationally it
makes sense
like the broader epistemic concept the
agent has to know what it could do yeah
it has to be known what could be done so
it's not that other terms are expunged
of
epistemic components it's just that
epistemic value is being used in a
pretty narrow way in equation
2.6 in the expected Information Gain
that does highlight something very
important but you you could do kind of
an epistemic inquiry
into how does one know that they know
and so
on sorry I just uh could you just
clearly differenti between this with
affordances which you said I
think what I saying is like so
affordances is the possible things which
a person can do at a particular moment
of time right exactly yeah and policies
like the the various policies you can do
but affordance is like at that specific
point of time what the agent does that's
basically the affordances so affordance
is very context sensitive yeah
affordances are actions that can be
taken in a
moment policies
are affordances over the time Horizon of
planning so if the time Horizon of
planning is just one then the policy
space is the affordance space if you're
talking about a time Horizon of two the
policy space Pi the list or vector Pi
that sums to one if you're talking about
a time Horizon of two is going to be the
length of affordances squared so like up
down left right in the moment
affordances and then planning Horizon of
two so the policy space of which
consideration is happening in would be
16 and then each of those
16 is going to have a prior so How
likely is it a priori and then if it
gets updated by expected free energy
it's going to get updated according to
the Information Gain and the pragmatic
value of each of those
policies where did you get the number 16
like four into four four squared oh okay
yeah and that's the kind of just like
it's like a chess
algorithm like the first pass approach
is just to expand your policy space
exponentially but then if you have more
than a couple of affordances at each
time St or you go more than a couple of
time steps deep the space of the policy
Vector becomes huge and then that
necessitates all these different
approaches to dealing with large policy
spaces ranging from like pruning of
policy
trees to setting up the problem a little
bit differently so that the branching is
less
exponential
so here's the narrow epistemic value
concept
just KL Divergence fancy e big
expectation
of KL
Divergence
between r q variational approximation of
hidden States Through
Time conditioned upon in both besides
the action everything is conditioned
upon the action and the only difference
is why Tilda so for that action how much
will those observations coming in update
my beliefs about hidden States through
time if the observations are expected to
be
moot then the Information Gain is low
because it's like it might as well not
be here if you expect there to be an
observation coming in that's super
informative then this is going to be a
large
Divergence and that's kind of perfectly
partitioned away from whether those
observations coming in are aligned with
what you expect and prefer to
see like pulling a slot machine like I
mean there's there's a lot of ways to go
with this but like you can imagine
there's two agents they're both pulling
a slot machine one of them is doing it
picking that policy because they're
seeking the information that the slot
machine provides next another one is
doing it because they believe that it's
going to come up in a favorable setting
for
them so that's kind of something people
people are exploring with a Precision
Psychiatry would be okay this person's
engaged in this repetitive behavior is
it because it's simply a habit and they
don't prefer to do it is this happening
because they actually prefer the outcome
that it
reaches is this happening because they
prefer an outcome and they've
misunderstood the consequences of the
action so they think that that action is
going to reach their desired
outcome but those from the outside look
exactly the
same hence designing like experiments
and cognitive models that could
differentiate why those are
different I have one question could you
please go back to that last equation
which is
showing yeah over here actually I don't
know what this what does the term mean
this Q the last one that that what is
the operator equal to and a triangle on
top any
idea defined as equal to
okay defined as equal by definition
two equal by definition
to like this is the joint distribution
so here's Q that's our variational
approximator that we
control this is a joint distribution of
X and Y conditioned upon Pi so it's like
there's kind of an X and A Y field
and we're making a probability density
over the X and the Y field conditioned
upon what action we're
selecting and then that is defined
as the joint product of our beliefs
about hidden State given
policy multiplied by basically the a
matrix the real mapping between hidden
States and observations so here's the
here's our our big underlying joint
generative model of the true temperature
in the room and the thermometer
reading conditioned upon
policy and we're going to be able to
break that down into well what is the
temperature of the room given our
policy and then what is the thermometer
reading given the true temperature of
the
room because of the factorizability the
the fact that the X and the Y were
orthagonal
gives us a sparsity that we can leverage
to
decompose The Joint distribution into
these two simpler
distributions
e
that's quite a thread
there it's like I've forgotten more than
I'll ever know just like how did this
happen deny the meaning of
awareness that's
um I do recommend I cannot remember the
name of the paper but there's like this
classic Marvin Minsky paper where he's
describing his take on AI at the time
this must be decades ago at this point
and at the end he hints at the idea that
uh and some kind of artificial
intelligence would have to have a model
of
itself and I just remember skimming that
paper and looking at active inference
and this idea that one has to have their
own model the of of themselves in the
world in order to kind of maintain that
that Markov blanket maintain that
separation between self and others so
that you can actually maintain your own
homeostasis maintain that um division
between between model an
environment kind of rambling on yeah and
like like we're aware of making
decisions on top of what we're not aware
of we're able to talk about this
semantics of like moving our hand around
because there's this kind of
infrastructural component that we're not
generally aware
of they call it self- evidencing
right yeah well self- evidencing let's
see where it comes
up self- evidencing is provided as
something like
the analogy to reward maximizing which
puts reward maximization as the unified
imperative in active inference where we
have surprise minimization or surprise
bounding about one's generative model as
the kind of key component we can think
about as I say one existential
imperative self-
evidencing but solipsism
is kind of a um deadend strategy so
self- evidencing doesn't just mean
observing oneself because over long
enough timelines that ends up becoming
maladaptive so that's kind of like well
how could novelty or creativity or
Aesthetics be brought
in when the unifying principle that
underlies behavior is to glean evidence
for one's model as it
is this is funny also like in chapter 10
has to come back to the preface so this
is I guess written by
Carl it's not just about
reading the free energy principle
equates existence with self-
evidencing can I tell a joke like I
don't know it's a joke or something they
they said that like all these people
this they're just worried about it the
mind will just shut off you know like
they will not do any self- evidencing
and then uh no nobody wants do that
something that is like Mo like like the
greatest fear among many people is that
okay they just don't want them they're
just worried about that the mind will
shut off one day and there'll be no
self- evidencing and everything will go
at us you know all this kind of
stuff h
sorry my level of jokes are with my kids
like the way I speak with my kids that
is the level of jokes I I don't know
better ones that's the sweet spot for
humor though it's like three to six
years yeah I mean it's it's
a strongly reinforced
theme that simple on through complex
systems are self-
evidencing to Garner sensory data
consistent
with an internal
model so it's like in the reward World
we'd have some temperature distribution
and then we have a second layer
Distribution on top of temperature how
rewarding those temperatures are and
then we pursue rewarding temperatures
like body temperature in the self-
evidencing world we have our basil
distribution of
temperature and then it's just explained
as action is taken to continually sample
from that distribution of preferred
temperatures whereas reward you need to
interpose with like another layer in
between the temperature and the
action so you're you have temperature
and then reward layer and then you're
taking actions based upon reward of
different actions here we have the basil
temperature layer and then we're taking
actions directly on that
distribution
um can I can I give a perspective of
self- evidencing as it relates to
meditation
yeah yeah okay I'm I'm not sure if I'm
in the right track like there will be
more learnings but self- evidencing like
it's actually people self-evidence is
there is a there's actually opposing
force between self- evidencing and
meditation basically because self-
evidencing is you want
to that's how I'm thinking like we know
ourselves by the evidences which are
provided from outside that is we are
inferring our evidences from the
knowledge from outside and um meditation
is trying to see what is really inside
so and and then there is one more this
concept marvelous concept of blankets
right so it's conditional Independence
you if the more you know about the
outside world if you know the blanket
States doesn't mean that you know more
about the inside world and that's like a
that's that's like I I I have just
fallen in love with this fundamental
concept like even if you know so much
about the external world but if the
blanket states are just this much then
knowing more about the external world
doesn't know more about yourself so
self- evidencing has its limits and uh
yeah so there is um there is some kind
of
a dynamic interplace so but but what I
think is this this this this
formulations and this concepts of active
influence can let us know so much about
the mind and how it works uh but there
will be there I don't know much but like
there will be challenges when we explore
the Realms beyond the mind it's the
Consciousness so I don't want to talk
about that because people can say and
they can have lot of theories but it may
not necessarily be right because this
conditional Bound by this Marco BL
blanket presents a very fundamental
um that's how that's like I don't know
if I phrased the appropriately but like
that is like this these two pillars are
what I'm basically thinking and how it
relates to meditation and these Concepts
yeah yeah it makes me think of U I don't
know if this directly relates to what
you're describing but this whole you
know just because you might know a lot
about the outside doesn't necessarily
mean you know a lot about the inside and
it makes me think about you know similar
to the rest of of kind of current
research and n neoscience uh active
inference also splits up uh when
describing different sensory modalities
as you know we don't just have like one
kind we have proprioception and
exteroception and interoception and all
three of them relate to inference and
kind of having to you know update
beliefs change your
attention um and and and kind of figure
out what to do and so in Tarot SE means
like reading your own body and reading
your own feelings even this this chapter
10 here relates um there's like a
section entire section that relates to
like emotion um in in trying to describe
that right like you have to actually
infer how you're feeling you don't just
automatically you know perfectly
precisely know and then suddenly an
emotion isn't so much like some kind of
innate perfectly inbuilt thing that we
just automatically like understand like
oh I'm sad it's like no you have to
infer that you have to like read what's
going on inside of you just as much as
you have to read what's going on outside
of you so suddenly your emotion is yeah
it's like a hypothesis of like oh based
on this feeling and this and this and
this other sensory information that I'm
getting from within me like how am I
feeling how am I doing let's put a
conceptual you know word on that name of
some emotion um yeah interesting uh
Kristoff you have a your hand
up uh yeah I just posted a link uh to a
talk by uh Shamil uh chandaria I think
he's affiliated with University of
Oxford and a bunch of other places and
it's a um Nono all Awakening yeah
computational neurom phenomenological
account uh which is basically entirely
based on the free energy principle
active in and it's an it's an incredible
talk it's the best summary of um
essentially various aspects of spiritual
practice from the perspective of
computational Neuroscience that they
have ever encountered and it's is really
really he goes really really deep um I
can tell you like from from my
perspective um understanding the free
energy principle um has been
enlightening to to say the least like in
in the in in the for me it's actually in
the lital sense there's a concept in
Buddhism which I believe is uh
Liberation by view um where um you know
a or or a practitioner
um receives a certain level of of of
Liberation by essentially understanding
um um certain truths about the nature of
reality without necessarily realizing um
uh for themselves a a certain meditative
attainments which are
um available to practitioners in the
path of insight so if you practice
mindfulness and concentration there is a
whole ladder of
um uh insights that you you essentially
climb you know the the the four janas
the the for the formless Realms and
finally the attainment of arand ship and
I find it that when I look at the
teachings of the Buddha particularly um
you know say reading the nikayas the
maim Manaya the middle length discourses
or s n the connected discourses and
thinking about them in terms of um free
energy principle and active inference um
the teachings of the Buddha are
incredibly clear like he is giving you
recognition models he's giving you means
of building your own um uh generative
models and it has a lot to do with
essentially making the pH phenomena that
happen in the mind opaque because
normally they're transparent to us we
don't know how they work we don't know
how the reality is uh constructed by the
mind we are not aware um of causes and
effects that give rise to certain
thoughts and feelings and and
perceptions and and mental formations
and concoctions and all these other
things and Buddha is giving you
essentially a
vocabulary so that you can um later on
label these things as they occur so he's
giving you a recognition model you can
say like ah this is a this is a
perception this is a mental formation
this is a feeling and feeling is born of
contact and contact is you know between
the internal sense basis and the
external sense basis and so on so forth
and then it that's for the purpose of
effectively building a generative model
um once you have the generative model
then you know you you get you become you
can become more introspective about your
own experience and
um the the goal of that is that your
experience becomes increasingly opaque
uh you see more aspects of it and so on
so forth and uh at the end of the path
you basically have complete insight into
how the reality is constructed by the
mind and that's why this phrase always
um recurs in in the Buddhist text that
you know um um the biku who completed
the path understands the the the the
birth is destroyed the holy life has
been lived what what what had to be done
has been done and there is no more
coming into any state of being it's not
a it's not a matter of you know question
like once once you get there you know
you know you're there so you know like
it's um I I think I I think there is a
the you know going back to this earlier
statement about the necessity of
updating the terminology and
taxonomy once you start looking at at
Buddhist teachings through this
perspective and if you look at this for
this modern perspective of computational
Neuroscience it's it's an Incredible
manual and it's so straightforward there
is no there is no um there's no doubt
about what you need to do and how how to
do it so I highly recommend um this talk
and uh you know it's a it's it's it's a
very fruitful area of
inquiry awesome
Francis thanks uh firstly uh I'd endorse
that uh thanks for um poting out to me
Kristoff uh
I uh watched it twice uh I'm sure I've
still got a hell of a lot more to get
out of it um it's
a really interesting
um secondly just kind of a related um
things to a very simple but it struck me
as interesting point uh which relates to
the whole idea of making the
transparent uh
opaque um and the fact that by making it
a p you can see it
which of course sounds a little
paradoxical um I've been thinking about
um mindfulness and kind of phenomenology
because it's really hard phenomenology
you know what is it that we're feeling
this stuff that we're not normally aware
of and of course a common mindfulness
technique is to label your
thoughts
and of course we normally think of that
is oh we're labeling them because we
want to then let them go but of course
by labeling them you make them
opaque and you could get a very good
stream of
Consciousness
um uh by just speaking these labels
loud um by
pursuing
the um St of mindfulness and the empty
mind you actually become aware of what's
in the mind and then um the third
thing just kind of going back to this
homeostasis
interception um and something even
simpler uh which is when I was first
started studying to be counselor I was
introduced
to uh
C's uh learning Loop
uh Kolb and that has four axes which are
it's kind of used in an educational
context and uh they have these kind of
rather long labels but then there's
another variation where the four
axes have one word labels and the labels
would
be uh action feeling thought
planning
and that
I've
explained that kind of gives us a model
of how we process our
feelings um and I explain it to people
in a counseling context why is it count
counselors are always asking you how
this makes you feel how you feel about
this
but you know we've got this engine this
cognitive engine up
here but how do we know what what's
stearing it what's the
point our feelings are where the rubber
hits the
road the road being our
well-being if we don't
know how we're
feeling we don't
know what to do with our
cognition
um and as you get further away from
basic biological homeostasis homeostatic
demands the biological
needs uh it gets harder and harder
to engage with are more complex in a
leads demands between say status and
connection uh should I pursue a job or
should I make time for being with my
partner uh and especially when you enter
this uh existential
anomaly all these brain power cognitive
power helps to increase our survival
that's what it's there
for but what happens when we get so much
cognitive power that we realize that
none of
the all all our paths lead to nons
survival in the end and into the
existential
challenge little dump mind dump there
can I just add something about labeling
um popped in my mind um as you were
speaking uh so that's there's a that's
mahasa tradition um uh is essentially to
just practice labeling all day long you
just label everything you do but um I
found I found I find this uh really
there's this really interesting paper um
from the deep Learning Community called
your classifier
is secretly an energy based model and
you should treat it as such and um I
think it's by Will
grall grad wolf I'm not sure what the C
name is but anyway so they show that if
you train um you know standard
classifier train on across entropy
objective like typical you know amist
class ifier neural network there's a way
of interpreting that as a energy based
model in such a way that you get
effectively the kind of unnormalized
probabilities that are required to
compute free energy and you effectively
get um uh a generative model for
free so this idea you know of labeling
by m and and other traditions in
Buddhism that all you have to do is
labeling
it's actually uh you know if you squint
your eyes at this paper and you say like
you know learning is kind of universal
and no matter how it's implemented the
the same sort of effects take place you
are B that that that is exactly the way
to build a generative
model um which I find I find it I I
think this this formal equivalence
between uh classification uh uh you know
the recognition and generative models
through energy based models specifically
which is just such a beautiful enrich um
formalism especially and and so
connected to to active inference um
that's going to be um is going to be
important so I I think this is a very uh
very interesting uh research Avenue of
how to connect active inference with um
this deep learning world and in some
sense you know like the because active
inference and free energy are so
Universal phenomena we know through this
argument that because they're apply to
anything that exists mathematic a prior
then these these systems must be
building models in the basian sense from
a certain perspective but it seems that
that equivalent is a lot deeper and much
more direct than just um you know this
kind of this is a mathematical principle
that has to be true kind of argument
it's actually can be shown how uh how
that happens so yeah uh fascinating
paper I highly recommend
it
yeah super cool it's fascinating to see
just like with this the integrative
approach of this last chapter how many
possible topics we could land on during
this conversation from from Deep
learning mathematical
formalisms uh the excesses of the the
human cognitive mind um
yeah it's it's it's really interesting I
personally just I find this kind of
first principles approach of act active
inference to just open doors to many
different
dialogues um and Francis I was finding
that to be very interesting I had like a
a kind of naive take on uh the idea of
like what what happens whenever you
start getting away from like a parent
homeo static needs um from an actm
perspective which is you know from a a
modeling perspective we're looking at
like an agent has their
preferences uh which are really their
their
expectations uh about preferences and
and so there are things that you expect
more to occur um and those those are you
know your your wants your needs and so
on might be some kind of colloquial
language we could assign to those uh
prior or those preferences and like the
idea might be that as a human being
navigates the world going forward an
increasingly more complex world you know
they they start to learn that they need
to do things Beyond simply oh I need to
drink water to say sh thirst um like a
variety of things navigating a kind of
Legal Financial social
occupational familial world that they're
in and it's almost like there's this
kind of expansion of uh of the state
space to learn about and uh with that a
kind of expansion of observations or
preferences to be realized in order to
to meet our wants and our our needs and
and and so to bring it back to this
discrepancy between like oh just keeping
your heartbeat uh regulated keeping your
your hydration levels reasonable like
suddenly there're all kinds of things I
want a nice house and I want a I want a
nice car or or conversely I I want to
have a very energy
efficient uh green uh lifestyle uh or
some such thing and and as it becomes
more complex it's like it just makes me
think of uh this classic Rolling Stones
song uh You Can't Always Get What You
Want
um and you know sometimes you can get
what you need um it also brings me back
to Buddhism and a lot of commentary upon
the role of of desire and its relation
with with suffering um just kind of you
know Li desire can ultimately be be
Limitless it can be transient uh it can
be something that sort of leads you
astray from the path um can be all kinds
of things and yeah I don't know I I
don't know if it's about kind of raining
in our our desires every once in a while
and really evaluating like what is
important here uh what do we really need
to do um and and how can we how can we
have our basic needs met then from there
I look at like look to neuroscience and
uh folks like um there's someone named
phel uh Sarah Felman Barrett she's great
she's done a lot of work on U uh emotion
and affect and and she's at least a
couple of times had some collaboration
with Carl friston and other folks in
active
inference um and she says like sometimes
you just need some good sleep some
sometimes whenever there's a kind of
overwhelmingness a kind of you begin to
interpret what's going on with you is
like anxiety uh you know in the extremes
of kind of catastrophic thinking of
trying to do everything all at once you
can imagine an active inference agent
trying to just minimize a ton of free
energy all at one time and it cannot
find the right policy to to accomplish
that within five seconds as much as it
might wish that such a thing were
possible um yeah it's really just you
know get some good sleep can you do that
and you know get some get some good
nutrients in your body and maybe get
whatever kind of exercise is reasonable
to you if if only like a nice walk um
apparent that can heavily change the the
inferential process uh and maybe can
help with straightening out thinking um
I could ramble on forever but yeah I'm
just kind of uh wrapping up the the
meeting here some thoughts throwing them
all
around I have to leave in one minute
because I've got a client uh on the hour
can I just uh yes please very thank you
so much and there's so much more love to
say and to talk about uh and I'm really
sorry that we've come to our last
session yes for this little fractal
cycle but we will all be able to suffer
more looking at pdps in the
future I'll be there with
luck okay thanks guys well thank you so
much thanks everyone yeah thank you okay
next week um we'll we'll just see what
happens we can um fill out the feedback
form
anonymously look through some of these
many comments and also I think now that
we are two years after the the
publishing of this book March uh
22 we can start to think about you know
we have RX and fur we have all these
other activities how do we want to
continue with the par our textbook group
so think about it over the next week and
then we'll discuss more L later thanks
thanks Andrew thanks
everybody thanks everybody it's been
amazing
yay thanks folks